here's an alternate interesting way to
find the sum of the first n positive odd
integers visually start with a square
array of cells as pictured here if we
imagine both dimensions to be n then we
have a total of n squ cells in this
array now let's go through and place two
tokens on every cell in the
array because there are n s cells and
two tokens per cell there are a total of
2 * n^ 2 tokens in this diagram
but now let's count the number of tokens
in a different way we can instead divide
the square array into triangular and
trapezoidal shapes each containing a
single diagonal line of tokens the first
one contains one token the next one
contains three tokens followed by five
tokens and so on each trapezoidal strip
contains exactly two more tokens than
the previous one so we get an ascending
list of consecutive odd integers ending
at the odd number 2 N minus one
but notice that this part of the diagram
can be repeated on the bottom half as
well and that means that the total
number of tokens is 2 * the sum of the
first n odd positive integers 1 + 3 + 5
and so on up to 2 nus 1 but now if we
cancel the two from both sides we get a
formula for the sum of the first n odd
positive integers in particular we see
that n^2 is equal to the sum where K
ranges from 1 to n of 2K minus 1 by
Counting tokens on a square array of
cells we've seen that the sum of the
first n odd positive integers is equal
to n^ S if you liked this visual proof
check out the description for other
visual proofs of the same fact and let
me know in the comments which one is
your favorite